<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King at New-Market, April 2, 1676 by Samuel Scattergood ...</title>
            <author>Scattergood, Samuel, 1646-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62324</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S843</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14320</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12594586</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12594586</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64032</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62324)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64032)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 333:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King at New-Market, April 2, 1676 by Samuel Scattergood ...</title>
                  <author>Scattergood, Samuel, 1646-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Hayes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published by His Majesties special command"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Job XXVIII, 28 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64032:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64032:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the KING AT <hi>NEW-MARKET April</hi> 2. 1676.</p>
            <p>BY SAMUEL SCATTERGOOD M. A. Fellow of <hi>Trinity College</hi> in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by his</hi> MAJESTIES <hi>ſpecial Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>CAMBRIDGE,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Hayes,</hi> Printer to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> 1676.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:64032:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64032:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Job 28.28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And unto Man he ſaid, Behold the fear of the Lord that is Wiſdom, and to depart from evil is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing that Man doth more earneſtly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue and hunt after then Wiſdom and Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and there is nothing that God is more deſirous that he ſhould obtain. And yet ſuch is the obſtinacy of our will, and the perverſeneſs of our Nature, that when God ſhews us the true wiſdom and the way to it, we will not follow his directions, but ſeek for it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our own fanſie, where it is never to be had: And then no wonder if in the end we prove ſuch fools, as to reap no other fruit of our labour but ſhame and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: no wonder if we meet with death
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64032:3"/>where we expected life, and find deſtruction in thoſe things wherein we ſought for hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. For it hath ever been the devils policy, even from the very beginning of the world, ſo cunningly to counterfeit this ineſtimable Jewel, that if we have not conſtant recourſe to Gods Word, to trie every thing we take for wiſdom by that unerring touchſtone, and weigh it carefully in the ballance of the Sanctuary, we may eaſily be deceived with a worthleſs trifle inſtead of this pearl of great price; we may embrace a ſhadow for a ſubſtance, and court ignorance and folly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Wiſdom and Underſtanding. Thus he overthrew our firſt Parents, by perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them to aſpire to a greater meaſure of Knowledge then God had thought fit to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon them; and he hath all along made uſe of the ſame temptation to the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of their Poſterity. He found it ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full then, and it hath been ſo ever ſince; and among all his wiles and ſtratagems he hath none by which he can ſo eaſily inveigle us as this; no bait ſo fair, ſo taking, and ſo univerſally prevalent among the Sons of men as this of Wiſdom and Knowledge. Nay I may in ſome ſenſe ſay that he hath no temptation at all by which he can move us but this alone. For did he not perſwade
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64032:3"/>men into a good opinion of themſelves, and that their wicked actions were wiſe and prudent, he could never induce them to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace his temptations: and therefore he ſutes them to every particular mans humour and diſpoſition. He offers not the ladder of Honour to the Sluggard, upon which he knows the ambitious man will venture his life and fortunes; but he brings a pillow to the one, and a ſcepter to the other: he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds eaſe, and idleneſs, and ſleep to the former, and perſwades him that wiſdom ſhall court him in a dream; and he ſhewes the latter <hi>all the kingdoms of the World and the glory of them,</hi> and tells him that Wiſdom is to be found no where but in the higheſt honour and moſt ſplendid preferments. He tells the Miſer that it conſiſts in riches, and that he muſt hoard it up in his coffers, he tells the Glutton that he ſhall find it in a dainty diſh, and he bids the Revenger drink it up in the blood of his enemies.</p>
            <p>But above all other perſons, thoſe who one would think ſhould be the beſt able to reſiſt his temptations (I mean the Learned) are often times moſt eaſily foiled by him. Their great learning and parts, moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent endowments, which might be very ſerviceable to Gods glory and the good of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64032:4"/>his Church, he perſwades them to abuſe in the maintaining of wrangling Diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and unneceſſary (and ſometimes dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous) Controverſies. By which means he rents the ſeamleſs coat of Chriſt, divides the Church into Schiſms and Factions, and ſhakes all into diſorder and Confuſion. He tells them, that to know Chriſt and him cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified is but a mean piece of knowledge, fit onely for men of weaker capacities to reſt content with. But as for them, he would have them fore aloft, and employ their time and ſtudy about deeper contemplations: examine what God was doing before he cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated the World: ſcan all the intrigues of his Providence: ſound the fathomleſs abyſs of his unſearchable Decrees: rifle, if it were poſſible, his moſt ſecret cloſet, and curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly prie into thoſe things which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed from Angels. This ſaith he, is Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and this is Underſtanding worthy to be acquired by men of Parts and Learning.</p>
            <p>And this vain and wicked Curioſity, this unlawfull thirſt after that Knowledge, which is hidden from us, was the occaſion of theſe words of my Text, and indeed of this whole Chapter. For <hi>Jobs</hi> three Friends were very bold, and fooliſhly poſitive in their aſſertions concerning Gods Decrees.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64032:4"/>They thought it was altogether inconſiſtent with his infinite Goodneſs to ſuffer either the Righteous to be in adverſity, or the Wicked to proſper in this world. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when they conſidered that their friend <hi>Job,</hi> who but a while before had been a mighty Prince, was all of a ſudden reduced to moſt extream poverty; and as it were in a moment, by unparalleled diſaſters, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of his whole Eſtate, his Children, his health, and brought down from a Throne to a Dunghill, they ſtood all ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed and aſtoniſhed at his unexpected cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; and inſtead of performing the duty of Friends, and comforting him in his affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, they moſt unfriendly and unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably cenſure him. And as if they had been of Gods privy Counſell, had ſtood by him, and throughly underſtood the whole deſign of his Providence in afflicting ſo ſeverely his ſervant <hi>Job,</hi> they preſently conclude him to be a moſt grievous ſinner; and that whatſoever ſpecious and fair ſhews he had made of Righteouſneſs and Integrity, yet they were all falſe and counterfeit, and that God had now unmasked him, and by his heavy judgements plainly diſcovered to all the world that he was a moſt notorious Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, and that he had marked him and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64032:5"/>ſet him up as a Butt againſt which he would ſhoot all the Arrows of his fury and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnation.</p>
            <p>All this <hi>Job</hi> hears and endures with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. He was ſenſible enough that God had afflicted him, and he knew too that it was not for his Hypocriſie, but for ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret end beſt known to his infinite Wiſdom: and therefore he enquires not after it, but labours to perform his own Duty, and to receive evil from the Hand of God, if he ſends it to him, as well as good, and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to bear whatſoever burden he laies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him; as one that was well aſſured that though <hi>in a little wrath he hid his face from him for a moment, yet with everlaſting kindneſs he would have mercy on him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is all the wiſdom he aſpires to, he meddles not with Gods ſecret counſell, nor ſearches after the Knowledge which he knew was <hi>too wonderfull for him.</hi> And what he himſelf practiſes he adviſes his Friends here to practiſe too, and blames them for preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo fondly to give an account of the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Gods Providence, and for thirſting after that Wiſdom which they can never at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to. 'Tis the ſubject of this whole chapter, in which he ſets forth moſt eloquently the impoſſibility of ever acquiring this Wiſdom,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64032:5"/>which God hath reſerved to himſelf as his own peculiar prerogative. For when he hath made a carefull enquiry after it throughout all the world; ranſak'd the Air, the Earth, the Sea; nay even hell it ſelf, and yet not found it: he concludes in the 23 Verſe of this Chapter that <hi>God underſtands the way thereof, and he knows the place thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God underſtands it, and he onely under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands it; and he will have none elſe to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, or meddle with it. He hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained another ſort of Wiſdom for Man to ſeek after, which though it will not ſatisfie the fond curioſity of every inquiſitive Brain that is ſtill longing for the forbidden Fruit, yet it will be ſufficient to make every one that attains to it wiſe unto Salvation. And this is the Wiſdom which is here recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to us in my Text with this empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall word <hi>Behold</hi> before it, to command our attention and to make us rouſe up our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and turn away our eyes from thoſe Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and that falſe Wiſdom which we are too ready to follow after, and fix them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the true. <hi>And unto Man he ſaid, Behold the fear of the Lord, that is Wiſdom, and to depart from evil is Underſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of which words I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, Firſt to ſhew what is here meane
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64032:6"/>by <hi>the Fear of the Lord.</hi> Secondly, what it is to depart from evil. And thirdly prove that to depart from evil in the Name and Fear of the Lord is the greateſt wiſdom that Man is capable of. Of theſe in order.</p>
            <p>And Firſt of the fear of the Lord. There is a fear of the Lord which is not Wiſdom, nor Underſtanding: nay it is Folly, it is Madneſs, it is Sin. I mean ſuch a fear as is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar only to wicked men; a fear that repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents God to them frowning; armed with thunder, and ready to take vengeance on their crimes: a very unwelcome gueſt in their Breaſts, which ſhews them as it were Hell in epitome, and gives them a taſte here of thoſe eternall torments which ſhall be their portion hereafter. This is the <hi>evil ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit from the Lord</hi> which troubled <hi>Saul.</hi> This is that fear which <hi>looſed the joints of</hi> Belſhazzars <hi>loyns, and ſmote his knees one againſt another,</hi> when he beheld the hand-writing againſt him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wall: that fear which made <hi>Cain a fugitive and a vagabond in the Earth;</hi> and drove <hi>Ahitophel</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> to deſperation. This is ſo far from being a bleſſing, that it is a curſe, a vexation, a tormenting Fury which wicked men labour all they can to chaſe out of their hearts: but alas it is all in vain; it haunts them ſtill, and will never depart
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64032:6"/>from them, till they depart from evil. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed perhaps it may ſometimes give them a little intermiſſion: but yet it returns again with the greater violence. No place is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure from it where wicked men can come; but it follows and purſues them every where; embitters all their joyes and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; torments them day and night, and affrights them even in their dreams. This is one fear of the Lord; but not that fear which is here meant in my Text: for if this be all the wiſdom man can attain to, ſurely then of all creatures he is the moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable.</p>
            <p>But we may go a degree further ſtill, and yet come ſhort of the true Fear of God. For there are ſome men that ſo fear Him, as that they will endeavour to abſtain from groſs and ſcandalous ſins: but not out of any true love they have for God, or any hatred they bear to ſin; but meerly out of Self-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, that they may (if poſſible) eſcape that vengeance which they know will one day be executed upon the Ungodly.</p>
            <p>I will not ſay that this fear is in all men a ſin: for it is in ſome a Virtue; and if it be not the Wiſdom here in the Text, yet it is at leaſt a good ſtep toward the obtaining of it. For as it is a true Maxim, that no man can all
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64032:7"/>of a ſudden become a moſt notorious ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: ſo it is as true one the contrary, that no man that hath been a ſinner (and ſuch we are all by Nature) can, without ſuch a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle as was wrought at the Converſion of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> in the twinkling of an eye become a Saint of the firſt Magnitude. No, we muſt be content to acquire this perfection by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees; we muſt creep, before we can go: be Babes in Chriſt before we can be ſtrong Men. We muſt <hi>paſs from ſtrength to ſtrength;</hi> from grace to grace, before we can <hi>appear before God in Sion.</hi> For certainly God would never have ſet before us Life and Death; never have propounded to us in his word Rewards and Puniſhments; nor have told us of a curſed and a bleſſed Eternity, if he did not allow us to fear the one, and to deſire the other.</p>
            <p>Nay this fear of Gods wrath is ſo far from being unlawfull, that it is abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. We muſt receive <hi>the Spirit of Bondage to fear, before we can have that of Adoption to cry, Abba, Father.</hi> We muſt be affrighted by the ſeverity of the Law, that we may be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible how great need we have of a Saviour. Our wounds muſt be cleanſed with a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſive before we pour in Oyl; and they muſt firſt ſmart with the Waters of <hi>Marah,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:64032:7"/>before they be refreſhed with the Balm of <hi>Gilead.</hi> We muſt fear God as an angry Judge, before we can love him as a tender Father; and we muſt tremble at his Terrours before we can adore his Mercy.</p>
            <p>But although this fear be good in thoſe Perſons who are carefull to improve it, and make it a ſtep to further Graces: yet it is ſinfull and wicked in all thoſe who reſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with this, and never aim at any higher Perfection; but think that they are good Chriſtians, if they abſtain from ſome ſins meerly out of hopes to eſcape damnation; though they never had (nor intend to have) any zeal for the Glory of God, nor any ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred for Sin: nay though indeed they love it at their heart, and could wiſh that there were no God to condemn them, nor Hell to torment them, that ſo they might have a licenſe to <hi>commit wickedneſs even with greedineſs;</hi> to <hi>drink iniquity like water;</hi> and ſecurely grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie all their luſts and corruptions. This is a ſecond degree of the fear of God; or indeed it is rather the fear of Hell; or to ſpeak moſt properly, 'tis the love of our ſelves.</p>
            <p>I come now to ſhew you what the true fear of God is, that fear which the Text tells us is Wiſdom. And this is ſuch a fear of God as proceeds from love; nay indeed it is nothing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64032:8"/>elſe but love; not of our ſelves, as the former fear, but of God, as the onely object that can deſerve our affections; as the greateſt, the onely Good, and the ſole author and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of all our Happineſs. So then this Grace may be ſtiled indifferently either Fear or Love. And it is no myſtery neither, Fear being ever an inſeparable companion of Love. For he that loves fears nothing more then to offend the perſon whom he loves: and if he have the ill fortune to do it, is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſubmit to any terms that will procure him a reconciliation. So it is with the Saints: they love God if not with an infinite, yet at leaſt with an ineffable love, far above all the World. And by how much the greater their Love is, ſo much the greater is their Fear too. So that if their Love be infinite (and it is ſo in reſpect of its Object, which is infinitely glorious and infinitely good) then the fear alſo which they have of miſcarrying in their Love, and diſpleaſing that infinite Majeſty which doth ſo well deſerve their Love and Adoration muſt be infinite too.</p>
            <p>This is that Fear which ſupported <hi>Job</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his mighty afflictions; enabled him to baffle all Satans deſigns; made him triumph over the fury and malice of Hell, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported him to that incomparable expreſſion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64032:8"/>of the confidence he repoſed in his God, <hi>Though he ſlay me, yet will I truſt in him.</hi> He knew that ſo long as he retained his integrity, however God ſeemed for the preſent to frown upon him, yet he would not <hi>caſt him off for ever.</hi> He knew that this ſtorm would ere long blow over, and that the ſun-ſhine of Gods favour would again enlighten him, and break through this black cloud, which for a while ſeemed to intercept it. But come what will on't; whether he live or die, he is reſolved both to live &amp; to die in the Fear of the Lord. This is his Load-ſtar, by which like a skilfull Pilot he ſteers through the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt. And though his riches have <hi>made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wings and are fled</hi> from him: though his children be all ſlain in a moment: though his friends brand him for an Hypocrite, and the wife of his boſom rail againſt him, and give him that deſperate and helliſh counſell, to <hi>curſe God and die:</hi> though he is become a laughing-ſtock to thoſe Perſons <hi>whoſe fathers once he would have diſdained to have ſet with the dogs of his flock:</hi> though he be thus forſaken of all the world, <hi>deſtitute, afflicted, tormented,</hi> and in all outward appearance forſaken even of God himſelf too, and made a ruefull ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle of his wrath and indignation; yet he <hi>ſins not</hi> for all this, <hi>nor charges God fooli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:64032:9"/>nay he cleaves to him the cloſer, well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that notwithſtanding he ſeemed to be his enemy, he was ſtill in reality his greateſt, his onely friend. And therefore he worſhips him as well when <hi>the days of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction have taken hold on him,</hi> as when <hi>God preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him, and made his candle to ſhine upon his head.</hi> He adores him as much on the Dunghill as on the Throne; praiſes his Name as well when his head is covered with aſhes, as if it wore a Diadem; and gives him thanks, when he hath left him nothing but a potſheard to ſcrape his ſores, as heartily as when he made him <hi>the greateſt of all the men of the Eaſt,</hi> and <hi>crowned him with loving kindneſs and tender mercies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I ſay is that fear which carried <hi>Job</hi> through ſuch a ſea of troubles; armed him againſt the ſtrength and policy of Satan, and made him a glorious Conquerour over Principalities and Powers. A fear which is as comfortable, as the former is terrible. That repreſents God to us as the greateſt evil, and drives us from him as from <hi>a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming fire:</hi> this makes us long for him (as in reality he is) as the greateſt Good, and wiſh that we <hi>had wings like a Dove</hi> that we might fly into his embraces. That is a fear of his Juſtice, and this of his Mercy; that a fear of puniſhment, and this of ſin. In a word,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64032:9"/>that is a flaſh from Hell fire, and this is a glimpſe of the joyes of Heaven. This then is the true fear of God which is here meant in the Text, and that fear which every man muſt get into his heart, as he tenders his eternall Salvation. I do not ſay that every man ſhall be damned that attains not to that Seraphick Perfection which was in <hi>Job,</hi> and S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and many others of Gods moſt eminent Saints: but certainly this I may faſely ſay, that whoſoever doth not either actually attain to it, or elſe heartily be wall and lament his want of it, and earneſtly beg of God that he would beſtow it on him, is very far from the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
            <p>And now what I promiſed to ſhew you in the next place, <hi>viz.</hi> what it is <hi>to depart from evil,</hi> I have in ſome meaſure performed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready: for this is a neceſſary conſequence and fruit of the <hi>fear of the Lord.</hi> I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tell you onely in a word what this evil is which we muſt depart from; and that is ſin: which, if we conſider it aright, is the onely thing in the world which we can properly call evil. For every thing is good that God hath made, and God hath made every thing elſe but ſin. That he utterly diſclaims; 'tis the work of the Devil and Man, and not of God. Nay 'tis ſo far from
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64032:10"/>being a work of his, that it defaces and deſtroys his work. 'Tis a burden which wearies the whole Creation; yea and the Creatour himſelf too: for the Scripture tells us that becauſe of this <hi>it repented the Lord that he had made Man on the earth, and it grieved him at his heart.</hi> The whole earth had been one continued and univerſall Paradiſe untill this day, had not ſin turned it into a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert. 'Tis this which hath <hi>made the Heaven o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our heads to be Braſs, and the Earth under us to be Iron,</hi> and cauſed it to bring forth <hi>thorns and thiſtles</hi> inſtead of <hi>wheat and barley.</hi> There had been no ſickneſs, had not ſin curſed the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry food we put into our mouths, and made us eat our poiſon. There had been no death, had not ſin armed him and ſharpned his ſting. There had been no Devil, had not ſin blackt him; and there had been no Hell, had not ſin kind led Gods wrath, and blown up that flame which never ſhall be quenched.</p>
            <p>It remains then that ſin, which is the cauſe of all this, is the onely true and reall evil in the world. And if ſo then ſurely to depart from ſuch an evil muſt needs be Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, which brings me to the third and laſt particular,</p>
            <p>Which is this, That to depart from this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64032:10"/>of ſin in the Name and Fear of the Lord, is the greateſt wiſdom that Man is capable of. But then we muſt be ſure to do it in the fear of the Lord. For otherwiſe though we have never ſo ardent an affection and love for Virtue; though we depart from vice with never ſo much care and vigilancy (for wholly depart from it no man can) we ſhall ſtill be but fools in the end. To <hi>fear god</hi> and to <hi>depart from evil</hi> are inſeparable companions: they are conſtantly joined together in Scripture; and <hi>what God hath joined let not Man put aſunder. Job</hi> was <hi>perfect and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right,</hi> ſaith the Text, <hi>one that feared God, and eſchewed evil. By the fear of the Lord men depart from evil,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon.</hi> And if we will <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Holineſs,</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> will tell us that it muſt be done <hi>in the fear of God.</hi> Theſe two are like Soul and Body; one cannot be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat without the other. <hi>Fear the Lord</hi> aright we cannot, except we <hi>depart from evil:</hi> and we cannot <hi>depart from evil,</hi> except we <hi>fear the Lord.</hi> This crowns all our actions, and makes our weak and imperfect endeavours after Holineſs to be accepted of in Heaven, through the merits of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And now that thus to depart from Evil is our greateſt Wiſdom, what need I ſpend many words to prove? Methinks, there
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64032:11"/>ſhould be no man ſo deſtitute of reaſon as not readily to acknowledge it. But though we have all reaſon enough to diſcern the excellency of this Wiſdom: yet in moſt men that is but a ſlave to their luſts, which tyrannize over them, and lead them captive with open eyes to meet their deſtruction. The ambitious man knows what a <hi>Kingdom is prepared for the Saints from the foundation of the World;</hi> and yet he will forfeit it for the breath of the Multitude. The Miſer knows that it would be better for him to <hi>lay up for himſelf treaſures in Heaven</hi> then upon Earth; and yet for all that he will <hi>have his inheritance on this ſide Jordan,</hi> and ſell his Soul that he may enrich his Heir. The Swearer knows that <hi>everyone that ſwears ſhall be cut off;</hi> and yet he prefers this gentile and modiſh embelliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his diſcourſe before all the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thems and Muſick of the Heavenly Chore. The Voluptuous man knows that the love of Chriſt to his Church <hi>paſſes the love of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men;</hi> and yet a ſmile from Beauty will move him more then all the melting entreaties and paſſionate importunities of a wooing Saviour. Thus though our reaſon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges this Wiſdom, yet our luſts diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avow it; and moſt of us I fear, are as careleſs in the practiſe of it, as we are apt to be loud
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64032:11"/>in its commendation. Seeing therefore that we have all by Nature ſuch a propenſity in us to gratifie our luſt rather then to obey our reaſon; I hope as I ſhall encourage all thoſe wiſe and happy Souls that have found this ineſtimable Treaſure, to the carefull keeping of it; ſo I ſhall not deterr thoſe unhappy Perſons from ſeeking it that have hitherto deſpiſed it, if according to my abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity I endeavour to evidence the worth of it briefly in theſe three following particulars. Firſt, it will deliver us from the greateſt Evil. Secondly, it will procure for us the greateſt Good. And Thirdly, all other Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom without this is but meer folly; but this of it ſelf alone, without the help and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of any thing elſe, which the world calls Wiſdom, is ſufficient to make us happy.</p>
            <p>Firſt, This <hi>departing from evil in the fear of the Lord</hi> is our greateſt Wiſdom, becauſe it will deliver us from the greateſt evil both here, and hereafter; from Sin and Hell. This Fear ſecures us from all other fears whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. He that fears not God fears every thing; and ſo long as he hath the Creatour for his enemy, thinks (as well he may) that the whole creation is armed againſt him for his deſtruction. There is nothing ſo mean and contemptible, but it can make him
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64032:12"/>tremble. He is jealous even of his own ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, leſt it ſhould be ſome Imp ſent to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour him. He ſympathizes with every ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king leaf he hears, and <hi>flees</hi> (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>when no man purſues him.</hi> His heart miſgives him at every thing, and he hath ſuch a continuall faintneſs upon him, as God threatens to ſend upon the rebellious Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites. He finds no true ſatisfaction in any thing; hath no comfort in any of his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, nor in any of his hours: but <hi>in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning he ſaith would God it were evening, and in the evening, would God it were morning.</hi> All the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies he makes uſe of, ſo long as he neglects this one in my Text, are but like water gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to one that is ſick of a feaver; ſo far from healing, that they augment and enrage his diſtemper. His Friends, his merry Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, and his full Bowls however they may ſeem for a while to mitigate his pain, to deafen the cries of his guilty Conſcience, and ſtave off that worm which gnaws him; yet he will find in the end that he takes his meaſures falſe, and that he drinks his Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon inſtead of his Antidote. For Conſcience will ſtill cry, yea and cry the louder too, the more he endeavours thus to ſilence it. And that Worm, though perhaps it forbear a little; yet it will return again more fiercely
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64032:12"/>then ever, and bite with a greater fury, with a ſharper appetite.</p>
            <p>What folly then, what madneſs is this, to harbour ſuch an implacable enemy in our boſom, as will ſuffer us to enjoy no peace, nor comfort in this World; yea and will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low us into the next World too, and there torment us to Eternity! And if it be the greateſt folly to run into ſuch an uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable evil as this; then certainly on the contrary, it muſt needs be the greateſt wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom imaginable to avoid it: or if we be fallen into it, to make a ſpeedy eſcape out of it again. And to do this no other courſe can be taken but that which my Text here preſcribes to us, <hi>To fear the Lord, and to depart from evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſecondly, as this Wiſdom delivers us from the greateſt evil, ſo it procures for us alſo the greateſt good. To reſcue a man from danger, and afterwards to take no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther care of him, is no extraordinary kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. But as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did by <hi>Joſeph,</hi> to exalt a man from a Priſon to a Palace; to knock off his iron ſhackles, and put him on a ring of gold; not onely to give him his freedom, but to make him Ruler over a mighty Kingdom, is a favour beyond all expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But this, and much more, doth this
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64032:13"/>Wiſdom do for us. If it had onely reſcued us from that everlaſting miſery to which we are all obnoxious; it had then been no common Benefactour: but it does more for us then ſo. It does not onely deliver us from Hell, but it entitles us to Heaven. It does not onely free us from the bondage and tyranny of Sin and Satan; but it advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces us alſo <hi>into the glorious liberty of the Children of God.</hi> It does not onely pluck us from the jaws of that roaring Lion; but it lodges us ſafe and ſecure in the arms of our Saviour.</p>
            <p>And now as he that hath not this Fear of God before his eyes fears every thing; ſo he that hath it fears nothing elſe, but God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. This Fear arms and fortifies him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whatſoever appears to other men for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable. He cares not, though the whole world be his enemy, while God is his Friend. He is not to be won by its enticements, nor daunted by its threatnings: but he ſtands firm and unſhaken upon this rock, exalted above its frowns and ſmiles.</p>
            <p>Conſcience, that is ſo terrible an enemy to him that fears not God, is his moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full friend (and it is as comfortable a friend, as it is a dreadfull enemy) It alwaies joyns with God, it is his Vice-roy to pronounce that ſentence on Earth which he paſſes in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64032:13"/>Heaven. While this therefore tells him that <hi>God is his refuge and ſtrength;</hi> he may ſay with the Pſalmiſt what follows, <hi>I will not fear though the Earth be removed, and though the Mountains be carried into the midſt of the ſea.</hi> This will enable him to comport and demean himſelf like a Child of God in all conditions. It will teach him with S. <hi>Paul, in whatſoever ſtate he is therewith to be content.</hi> This will ſweeten every bitter cup. This will lighten the burden of his affliction. This will <hi>make all his bed in his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> This will fill him with joy even at the hour of his death, and enable him to deliver up his ſoul into the hand of God with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and full aſſurance of a bleſſed Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. And then in that <hi>great and terrible day of the Lord, wherein the Heavens being on fire ſhall be diſſolved, and the Elements ſhall melt with fervent heat;</hi> when the whole World ſhall tremble, and neither Heaven nor Earth be able to abide the dreadfull approach of that great Judge, but both <hi>ſhall paſs away</hi> and be conſumed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him; when <hi>the Wicked ſhall call in vain to the Mountains and Rocks to fall on them, and all the tribes of the earth ſhall mourn:</hi> Then ſhall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhew it ſelf to be a moſt faithfull friend; embolden him to <hi>lift up his head with joy;</hi> plead for him againſt all his Accuſers, and through the merits and mercy of Chriſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64032:14"/>acquit him at that grand Tribunal: Then ſhall this Wiſdom as it hath freed him from the greateſt evil, from ſin and hell; ſo alſo confer upon him the greateſt Good, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt him with eternall Holineſs and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs.</p>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly, All other Wiſdom without this is but meer Folly; but this of it ſelf alone, without the help and concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of any thing elſe which the world calls Wiſdom, is ſufficient to make us eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally happy. For in what elſe ſhall we place Wiſdom, if not in the <hi>Fear of the Lord?</hi> Shall we place it in pleaſures? Alas there are none to be found any where, but <hi>at Gods right hand.</hi> The pleaſures of this world are but torments: they ſeem perhaps to delight us a little for the preſent; but ſoon after they ſting us to the heart. Shall we place it in Riches? They are but fading and periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enjoyments, and muſt ſhortly leave us: and if they ſhould tarry with us never ſo long, the wiſe man tells us, that <hi>they profit not in the day of wrath.</hi> Shall we place it in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour? there is nothing more uncertain then that: for though it be never ſo ſplendid and glorious for a while; yet it muſt ere long be <hi>laid in the duſt.</hi> Indeed Honour and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is ſo far from being an ordinary and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64032:14"/>thing; that if we conſider it aright, it is perhaps the greateſt temporal Bleſſing that God hath to beſtow upon Man: and Kings and Rulers have this happineſs above the reſt of Mankind, that they have power to do more good in the world, and to bring greater glory to God then inferiour per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and conſequently may procure for themſelves a more honourable Throne, and a brighter Crown in Heaven. All ſhall be there full of glory, and every one perfectly ſatisfied and content with his own conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but yet there ſhall be a difference; and while ſome ſhall but twinkle as the Stars, others ſhall ſhine as the Sun. The meaneſt Subject that hath been loyal to his King, and obedient to his God, ſhall at the laſt day be rewarded with an incorruptible Crown; for we ſhall all be <hi>Kings and Prieſts unto God.</hi> But I know not any thing in Scripture that doth not freely permit a godly and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Prince to hope to be as highly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced above his Subjects in Heaven, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he was here one Earth, if he manages his Sceptre with this Wiſdom here in my Text, which will be ſure to eſtabliſh his Throne, and make his Crown to flouriſh. Again, ſhall we place Wiſdom in Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning? This alſo, if it be ſanctified by Grace,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64032:15"/>is a very great Bleſſing: but without that it is as great a Curſe; without Grace it will but enable a man to ſin more powerfully: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that he that hath a learned head, and an unſanctified heart, may almoſt ſtand in competition with the Devil himſelf, who ſhould be the Maſter worker of iniquity, and gain moſt Proſelytes to the kingdom of Darkneſs. The ignoranteſt Peſant may make a ſorry ſhift to grope out his way to hell, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven blindfold: but the learned Atheiſt ſees ſo many roads to it, that he will pick and chuſe his way ſo diſcreetly, as to be ſure to provide for himſelf one of the hotteſt places. S. <hi>Paul</hi> had continued a Perſecutour to his dying day, notwithſtanding all that Learning that he got <hi>at the feet of Gamaliel,</hi> had he not alſo learned Chriſt. And therefore he profeſſes this to be the onely true Wiſdom: for, ſaith he, <hi>I count all things but loſs for the excellency of the knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus my Lord,</hi> Phil. 3.8.</p>
            <p>But to riſe yet one ſtep higher then Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning can advance us. Suppoſe God ſhould endue us with the Spirit of Propheſie to foretell things to come; or with a power to work Miracles and to caſt out devils; yet we ſhould be never the nearer to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for all this, without the Wiſdom here in my Text. For one of theſe faculties was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64032:15"/>on <hi>Balaam;</hi> and yet, for all his good wiſhes 'tis probable that he died not <hi>the death of the Righteous:</hi> and the other on <hi>Judas;</hi> and yet himſelf was <hi>a Devil.</hi> Alas what were we the better, if we knew the hour of our death; if we knew too that from that hour our everlaſting puniſhment ſhould bear its date? What would it profit us, though we knew the minute when the Archangel ſhould begin to ſound his Trump; if we knew withall that that ſound ſhould ſummon us to hear the Sentence of our eternall condemnation? Such Wiſdom as this would be ſo far from making us hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, that it would antedate our miſery, and torment us before the time. All other things then, ſo long as we want this <hi>one thing</hi> which <hi>is needfull,</hi> will be but weak Advocates to plead our cauſe before Chriſts Tribunal.</p>
            <p>And as all the Wiſdom of the world will profit us nothing without this, ſo this of it ſelf alone is ſufficient to make us happy. He that hath never been either at <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Athens;</hi> nay though he knows not ſo much as one letter of the Alphabet, is wiſe enough, if he hath but learned the Croſs of Chriſt. He that is never ſo poor, hath wealth enough, if he be but <hi>rich in Faith;</hi> and though he appear to men <hi>as having nothing, yet poſſeſſes all things. The Brother
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64032:16"/>of low degree,</hi> that is never ſo mean and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible in the eyes of the world, if he hath but this Wiſdom in the Text, is highly honourable in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>But to what purpoſe ſhould I ſpend any more words in illuſtrating the incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable worth of this Wiſdom, which as it deſerves all, ſo it needs no commendation? I will therefore detain you no longer, but conclude all in the words of the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> cap. 9. v. 23, 24. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, Let not the Wiſe man glory in his wiſdom, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let the Mighty man glory in his Might; let not the Rich man glory in his Riches. But let him that glories glory in this, that he underſtands and knows me, that I am the Lord which exerciſe loving kindneſs, judgement, and righteouſneſs in the Earth: for in theſe things I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
